Guide to the David H. Greene Collection of Sean O'Casey Letters 1944 - 1962 MSS.236
Fales Library and Special Collections
David H. Greene Collection of Sean O'Casey Letters
1944-1962
Fales Library and Special Collections
O'Casey, Sean, 1880-1964
Greene, David H. (David Herbert), 1913-2008
MSS.236
0.25 Linear Feet in 1 half manuscript box
Sean O'Casey (1880-1964) was an Irish playwright and memoirist noted for his portrayal of the lives of Ireland's working class and poor. O'Casey is assoicated with Dublin's Abbey Theatre, and his significant plays include "The Shadow of a Gunman", "Juno and the Paycock", "The Plough and the Stars", "Cock-A-Doodle Dandy", and "The Bishop's Bonfire". Casey also produced a six-volume autobiography. This collection consists of letters written by O'Casey to David H. Greene, a leading scholar of Irish literature. Greene edited 1000 years of Irish Prose, An Anthology of Irish Literature, and co-edited The Matter with Ireland, a collection of writings from George Bernard Shaw. He also co-wrote the authorized biography of Irish dramatist John M. Synge. O'Casey and Greene met in the 1930s, and continued a friendship and correspondence until O'Casey's death in 1964.
Provenance
The David H. Greene Collection of Sean O'Casey Letters were donated to the Fales Library in 2005 by David H. Greene from his personal papers.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged chronologically.
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence
Biographical Note
Sean O'Casey (1880-1964) was an Irish playwright and memoirist noted for his portrayal of the lives of Ireland's working class and poor. O'Casey was born in Dublin in 1880 and struggled in his early life with poverty and illness. He became involved in the Irish nationalist movement, was noted for his socialist and communist political beliefs, and was often critical of the Catholic Church. O'Casey's first significant success as a dramatist came with the acceptance and production of The Shadow of a Gunman by the Abbey Theatre in Dublin in 1923. The Abbey Theatre would produce several of his subsequent plays, including Juno and the Paycock, and The Plough and the Stars, which caused riots after being criticized as anti-Irish. In 1926, O'Casey went to London on what was intended to be a short visit, but decided to remain in England as a result of disputes with the Abbey Theatre and several figures in the Irish literary community. He continued to write and produced several other notable dramatic works, including Purple Dust, Red Roses for Me, Cock-A-Doodle Dandy, and The Bishop's Bonfire. O'Casey also produced an autobiography that was released in six individual volumes from 1939 to 1954. Sean O'Casey is regarded as one of the leading Irish playwrights of the 20th Century. (1)
David H. Greene (1913-2008), was a leading scholar of Irish literature and professor at New York University. Greene edited 1000 years of Irish Prose, An Anthology of Irish Literature, and co-edited The Matter with Ireland, a collection of writings from George Bernard Shaw. He also co-wrote the authorized biography of Irish dramatist John M. Synge, J.M. Synge, 1871-1909. O'Casey and Greene met in the 1930s while Greene was a graduate student at Harvard University, and continued a friendship and correspondence until O'Casey's death in 1964. (2)
Sources:
(1) daRin, Doris. Sean O'Casey. New York: Frederick Ungar Publishing Co., 1976.
"Sean O'Casey, Irish Playwright, is Dead at 84." New York Times, September 19, 1964. (2) Hevesi, Dennis. "David H. Greene, Scholar of Irish Literature, Dies at 94." New York Times, July 13, 2008.
Scope and Content note
The David H. Green Collection of Sean O'Casey Letters consists of one series containing correspondence primarily from Sean O'Casey to David H. Greene from 1944 to 1962. The letters contain comments by O'Casey on Irish literature, theater, and criticism, as well as discussions of his personal life. There are two letters written by Eileen O'Casey, Sean O'Casey's spouse, on his behalf while he was ill. In addition, there is one letter addressed to Catherine Greene, David Greene's spouse. A small number of letters include enclosures such as newspaper clippings and other correspondence.
Related Materials
Fales Manuscript Collection (MSS.001)
O'Casey, Sean, |d 1880-1964 |x Correspondence.; Authors, Irish |y 20th century |v Correspondence; Dramatists, Irish |y 20th century |x Correspondence.; Irish literature |y 20th century.; Irish drama -- 20th century.; Greene, David H. (David Herbert), 1913-2008; O'Casey, Sean, 1880-1964; Abbey Theatre
- Series I: Correspondence
  Scope and Content note
  The series contains correspondence primarily from Sean O'Casey to David H. Greene from 1944 to 1962. The letters contain comments by O'Casey on Irish literature, theater, and criticism, as well as discussions of his personal life. There are two letters written by Eileen O'Casey, Sean O'Casey's spouse, on his behalf while he was ill. In addition, there is one letter addressed to Catherine Greene, David Greene's spouse. A small number of letters include enclosures such as newspaper clippings and other correspondence.
  - Autograph Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Autograph Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Autograph Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Autograph and Typescript Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Autograph Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Autograph Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Autograph and Typescript Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Typescript Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Autograph and Typescript Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Autograph and Typescript Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Autograph Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Autograph and Typescript Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Autograph and Typescript Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Typescript Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Autograph Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Autograph and Typescript Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)